Narrator: Part 2
R: Erm, and then, of course, as you say, life is full of stories,
life is full of adventures and misadventures, light and shade,
and then you had this devastating diagnosis of cancer,
um, and that, for a moment, put you completely out of the game.
J: I’d – yes, it did. I was 38 years old, my son was just two, I’d sold my business to Estée Lauder,
I was having the time of my life, and a curve ball…it came from nowhere, I
didn’t anticipate it, didn’t expect it, didn’t deserve it, but no one does.
And I was, um, I’d found a lump in my breast, went to have it checked,
thought it was a cyst and it wasn’t, it was a very, very aggressive form of breast cancer,
and I was given a pretty grim diagnosis of under a year.
And I remember sitting there and putting that same head on as [when]
I was the little girl that stood on the chair and wouldn’t take no for an answer, and I thought,
‘No one’s going to tell me when I’m going to die, I’m going to fight this and – and try and survive.’
So, I went to New York City.
I was one of the first women to take chemotherapy in a very different way,
in much longer periods but shorter spaces of time, and I spent a year, surgery after surgery,
lost my hair, lost half my body, and then found a way of putting my life back together again.
Came through all of that, and was given…you’re not given the all-clear straightaway,
but I was…I was told, you know, ‘It’s time to go back and live your life.’
And it’s like walking a tightrope without a net, it’s a really scary moment.
And then I realized I couldn’t smell: that chemotherapy had taken away my sense of smell.
R: How did that – how did you discover that?
J: Because I couldn’t…All I could smell was this…I mean,
I had been on Adriamycin, Cytoxan, Taxol, Taxotere – you name it, they’d thrown it.
And let me tell you, I’m all clear still. It worked.
R: Great, yeah.
J: So, you have to balance life.
But, all I could smell was metal, and all I could taste was metal, so I couldn’t create fragrance,
and it was the most devastating thing for me, because that’s who I am.
R: It’s your creativity.
J: It’s – it’s how I interpret life, it’s…And so, I was left by this person,
and that was why I decided to – to walk away and leave…um,
I couldn’t bear to be around something I couldn’t be creative with,
and I didn’t want to be the figurehead.
And so, I made the decision to leave the business that I’d founded.
P: Miraculously, five years later,
Jo had regained her sense of smell and set up a new fragrance company.
J: Well, 2011 I launched, er, Jo Loves, and, um, so, she’s seven years old now, and is now flying.
But it – I promise you, it was a very tough journey getting there,
and the first two years I wanted to quit every single day. It was just excruciatingly difficult.
R: Harder the second time around…?
J: Much harder.
R: Why?
J: Um, I made every mistake in the book, the second time round.
I got the packaging wrong, I got the distribution wrong…I know, I know.
P: But, why?
J: I don’t know, I don’t know. We’re people, we’re human beings, we make mistakes. And when…
G: Yeah…You don’t expect that of someone who’s been so successful, though.
J: Well, that’s what the world thinks, but actually, in reality…
But if I hadn’t done it, I hadn’t made those mistakes
– I am living the most amazing adventure of life right at this moment.
I wouldn’t be here. So, you learn from those mistakes, don’t you?
G: You learn from your mistakes, exactly…